Chicago & Northwestern Transportation Company Records 5533
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Chicago & Northwestern Transportation Company Records
1907-1971
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Chicago & Northwestern Transportation Company (CNW)
5533
10 cubic feet
10 linear ft.
Agreements, records (documents).
Collection includes correspondence concerning grievance claims and work rules; agreements with major railroad unions; statistics on workers' compensation and hours; miscellaneous legal documents concerning disputes brought before federal boards; and circulars from industry conferences, concerning company-labor relations. Also includes documentation of the Chicago and North Westerns' merger with the Chicago Great Western Railway. Select information from predecessor carriers is also found in this collection.
3833932
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, March 13, 2014
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, May 30, 2019
Biographical / Historical
William Butler Ogden, a railroad investor (b. 1805), took over the Madison and Beloit Railroad in Wisconsin, extended the lines and later, after the financial troubles of 1857, reorganized the line into the Chicago and North Western Railway, into which the Galena and Chicago Union Railroad was also merged.
Biographical / Historical
The Chicago and North Western Transportation Company [CNW] was a Class I railroad in the Midwestern United States, often called the North Western. The CNW also called itself the "Pioneer Railroad," because one of its predecessor lines, the Galena and Chicago Union Railroad, was the first railroad to run out of Chicago. The railroad operated more than 12,000 miles of track in seven states (Wisconsin, Iowa, Nebraska, South Dakota, Illinois, Missouri, and Michigan) before retrenchment in the late 1970s. At the height of the railroad era, the CNW was one of the most profitable of the Midwestern railroads and one of the longest railroads in the United States because of mergers with other railroads, such as the Chicago Great Western Railway, Minneapolis and St. Louis Railway and others.
The CNW's earliest predecessor, the Galena and Chicago Union Railroad [GCU], was chartered in 1836. In 1848, it operated the first steam locomotive out of Chicago. Despite this early success, the GCU had many problems, including an inability to build tracks to Galena, Illinois, one of its supposed terminals, and instead had to rely on an interchange built by the Illinois Central to reach the city. These problems led to it being purchased by William Butler Ogden. Ogden was the first mayor of Chicago and a railroad investor. Ogden had already taken over the Madison and Beloit Railroad in Wisconsin and extended its lines. After the financial trouble of 1857, Ogden founded and incorporated the CNW. The CNW was chartered on June 7, 1859, by the legislatures of Illinois and Wisconsin. Five days previously, it had purchased the bankrupt Chicago, St. Paul and Fond du Lac Railroad. Ogden now controlled numerous roads in the Midwest; by 1865, they were merged into one system, the CNW, with over 850 miles of track. Ogden left the company in 1868 and became president of the Union Pacific. This was after one of CNW's predecessor lines, the Cedar Rapids and Missouri River Rail Road, had reached Council Bluffs, Iowa, in 1867, establishing a direct interchange with the Union Pacific, the first transcontinental railroad. By the end of the 19th Century, the CNW operated on over 7,000 miles of track, connecting such cities as Chicago, Omaha, Milwaukee, Duluth, Rapid City and the Twin Cities.
The CNW opened its Proviso Yards in Chicago in 1929. This facility was the largest of its kind when it was built, containing 224 miles of tracks and a huge diesel shop. The CNW was a "granger" railroad, primarily serving agricultural businesses. Potatoes were ones of its main crops, and the Potato Sheds in its Wood Street Yards were the largest in the world. It also did extensive business in transporting sugar beets, corn and wheat. The CNW also operated extensive passenger lines, including serving as one of the main commuter lines for Chicago.
The CNW was unique among American railroads in that it ran on a left-hand main, which meant that traffic was routed to the left instead of to the right. This was common among railroads built by British companies, but not among American ones.
The CNW was badly affected by the Great Depression, declaring bankruptcy in 1935 and not emerging until 1944 with the surge in traffic that happened because of the mobilization of men and goods for World War II.
The post-war period saw another sharp decline in the CNW's profits, as freight increasingly moved to the highways and the CNW had a large amount of secondary trackage that was a massive drain on the company since the industries on these lines no longer used the rails to ship their goods. However, even with this reality, the CNW still made major acquisitions in the late 1950s and 1960s, gaining control of the Litchfield and Madison Railway in 1958, the Minneapolis and St. Louis Railway in 1960, and the Chicago Great Western Railway in 1968.
In 1972, the CNW was sold to its employees and renamed the Chicago and North Western Transportation Company. In 1985, the employee owned stock of the company was transferred to the newly formed CNW Corporation, ending the employee owned period. By 1995, track sales and abandonment had reduced the total mileage of the CNW to about 5,000 miles. The company was purchased by Union Pacific [UP] in April 1995 and ceased to exist as an independent entity.
Scope and Contents
Inclusive date range: 1907-1971
Bulk dates: 1950-1968
This collection consists of the records of the Chicago North Western Transportation Company's records. The majority of materials in this collection were produced by the CNW's predecessor railroads: specifically the Minneapolis and St. Louis Railway [M&StL], a small granger railroad acquired by the CNW in 1960; and the Ft. Dodge, Des Moines, and Southern Railroad, an inter-urban electric line, acquired by the CNW in 1968.
The collection has been arranged into 14 series:
Series I: Correspondence
Series II: Circulars
Series III: Minneapolis and St. Louis Railway Motive Power and Operations Data
Series IV: Dispute between the Minneapolis and St. Louis Railway and the Federated Shop Crafts
Series V: Employee Manuals
Series VI: National Railroad Adjustment Board Decisions and Awards
Series VII: Federal Railroad Legislation and Emergency Boards
Series VIII: Carrier Mergers
Series IX: National Rules Movements
Series X: Local Agreements, Conferences, and Reports
Series XI: Clerks, Represented by BRAC
Series XII: Yardmasters, Represented by Railroad Yardmasters of America
Series XIII: Dispatchers, Represented by the American Train Dispatchers Association
Series XIV: Agreements, Historic, Between Various Labor Organizations and Ft. Dodge, Des Moines, and Southern Railroad
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5003 P: U.S. President's Railroad Commission Photographs 5174m: Wheeling and Lake Erie Railway Company Work Agreements, Regulations, Wage Book and Book of Rules 5550: Wheeling & Lake Erie Railway Company Offices of Vice-President & General Manager Representative Files
Arrangement
Series I: Correspondence, 1926-1958
Series II: Circulars, 1945-1958
Series III: Minneapolis and St. Louis Railway Motive Power and Operations Data, 1930-1949
Series IV: Dispute between the Minneapolis and St. Louis Railway and the Federated Shop Crafts, 1920-1953
Series V: Employee Manuals, 1941-1968
Series VI: National Railroad Adjustment Board. Decisions and Awards, 1952-1955
Series VII: Federal Railroad Legislation and Emergency Boards, 1918-1951
Series VIII: Carrier Mergers, 1958-1968
Series IX: National Rules Movements, 1940-1960
Series X: Minneapolis and St. Louis Railway. Local Agreements, Conferences, and Reports, 1926-1960
Series XI: Clerks, Represented by the Brotherhood of Railway, Airline and Steamship Clerks, Freight Handlers, Express and Station Employees [BRAC], 1921-1960
Series XII: Yardmasters, Represented by Railroad Yardmasters of America [RRYMoA], 1922-1960
Series XIII: Dispatchers, Represented by the American Train Dispatchers Association, 1921-1960
Series XIV: Agreements, Historic, Between Various Labor Organizations and Ft. Dodge, Des Moines, and Southern Railroad, 1907-1947
Collective bargaining -- Railroads -- United States; Employee fringe benefits -- Railroads -- United States -- Statistics; Railroads -- Employees -- Transfer -- United States; Supervisors, Industrial -- Labor unions -- United States; Grievance procedures -- Railroads -- United States; Railroads -- Employees -- Job vacancies -- United States; Labor discipline -- Railroads -- United States; Layoff systems -- United States; Personnel directors; Occupations -- Classification; Railroads -- United States -- Employees; Railroads -- Personnel management -- United States; Sex discrimination in employment -- United States; Wages -- Railroads -- United States; Women -- Employment -- United States; Work rules -- Railroads -- United States; Working conditions -- Railroads -- United States; Braese, O. H.; Jewell, B. M.; Leighty, G. E.; Leiserson, William.; Thompson, E. C.; 40-Hour Week Committee; American Federation of Labor; American Federation of Labor. Railway Employees' Department; American Telegraph Dispatchers Association; Association of Western Railroads; Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees; Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen; Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers (U.S.); Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen; Brotherhood of Railway, Airline, and Steamship Clerks, Freight Handlers, Express, and Station Employes; Chicago and North Western Railway Company; Chicago Great Western Railway Company (1940-1968); Eastern Carriers' Conference Committee; Ft. Dodge, Des Moines, and Southern Railroad; Great Northern Railway; Minneapolis & St. Louis Railroad; Order of Railroad Telegraphers (U.S.); Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen; Order of Railway Conductors of America; Railroad Yardmasters of America; Southeastern Carriers' Conference Committee; United States. Board of Conciliation and Investigation; United States. Interstate Commerce Commission; United States. National Mediation Board; United States. National Railroad Adjustment Board; United States. National Railway Labor Panel; United States. National War Labor Board (1942-1945); United States. Railroad Labor Board; Western Carriers' Conference Committee
3833932
- Series I: Correspondence, 1926-1958
  Scope and Contents
  The correspondence chiefly consists of grievance claims and discussions of the rules surrounding the claims. The major claims regard seniority, including seniority dating, rights, status, and rosters; claims for time- and-a-half; wage rates, including adjustments and wage differentials, apprentice rates, wage increases, and rates for various positions; claims for overtime; claims for back pay; time claims as a result of position abolishment, sickness, and injury; mileage claims; claims regarding reductions in the work force; displacement claims; and vacation claims.
  Other claims regard working conditions, including the issues of inadequate facilities, sanitation, drinking water, lockers, and hazardous conditions; women workers, including the issues of dismissal for marrying, wages, and employment due to the labor shortage; and claims regarding the workweek and the workday, including the seven-to-six- day workweek, six-hour workday, and five-day work assignments. Finally, other grievance cases involve disciplinary actions and suspension; layoffs; transfers; dismissals; reclassifications; and posting of positions in accordance with local agreements.
  Major correspondents include officers of the Minneapolis and St. Louis Railroad, of the Great Northern Railway, and of the Chicago Great Western Railway. Other major correspondents include officers of the following unions: the Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen [BRT], the Order of Railway Conductors [ORC], the Brotherhood of Railway, Airline and Steamship Clerks, Freight Handlers, Express and Station Employees [BRAC], the Order of Railway Conductors [ORC], and the Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees. Finally, there are numerous pieces of correspondence with officers of the Association of Western Railroads.
  Individual correspondents include G.E. Leighty, (president of the Order of Railroad Telegraphers), E.C. Thompson (executive secretary, National Mediation Board), William M. Leiserson (chairman, National Railway Labor Panel), B.M. Jewell (president, Railway Employees Department, American Federation of Labor) and O.H. Braese (president, American Telegraph Dispatchers Association).
  Additional pieces of correspondence are also found in the other series where indicated.
  - Correspondence, 1926-1929 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1928-1929 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Includes arbitration agreement between BRAC and Norther Pacific
  - Correspondence, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    January to March 1932
  - Correspondence, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    April to July 1932
  - Correspondence, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    August to December 1932
  - Correspondence, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    January to June 1933
  - Correspondence, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    July to December 1933
  - Correspondence, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    January to April 1934
  - Correspondence, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    May to August 1934
  - Correspondence, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    September to December 1934
  - Correspondence, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Includes mediation agreements, ICC filings, and court filings
  - Correspondence, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    January to July 1940
  - Correspondence, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    September 1940. Contain Memorandum of Agreement with BRAC.
  - Correspondence, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    October to December 1940
  - Correspondence, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    January to April 1941
  - Correspondence, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    May to July 1941
  - Correspondence, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    August 1941
  - Correspondence, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    September to December 1941
  - Correspondence, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    January to April 1942
  - Correspondence, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    May to June 1942
  - Correspondence, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    July to December 1942
  - Correspondence, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    January to June 1944
  - Correspondence, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    July to December 1944
  - Correspondence, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    January to June 1945
  - Correspondence, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    July to December 1945
  - Correspondence, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    January to October 1947
  - Correspondence, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    November 1947
  - Correspondence, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    December 1947
  - Correspondence, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    January to June 1948
  - Correspondence, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    July to December 1948
  - Correspondence, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    January to May 1950
  - Correspondence, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    August 1950
  - Correspondence, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    September 1950. Contains memorandum of Agreement between M&St.L Rwy and ORT.
  - Correspondence, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    July to December 1956
  - Correspondence, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Series II: Circulars, 1945-1958
  This series consists of two sets of circulars. One set, from the Association of Western Railways [AWR], contains updates on agreements member carriers have entered into with various labor organizations. They also contain the text of the Agreements. AWR Circulars also contain information on decisions by various boards of adjustments based on interpretations of the previously mentioned agreements. Some of the circulars have attached correspondence, discussing how these interpretations affect either the carrier or their employees.
  The second set of circulars come from the CNW itself. These circulars, issued by the personnel department, inform employees about updates and changes to the Rules, Agreements, and Schedules made between the carrier and the various labor organizations that represent the employees in negotiations. The circulars also interpret the changes, and inform the different classes of employees how the changes affect them.
  - Circulars for the Association of Western Railways, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    June to August 1951
  - Circulars for the Association of Western Railways, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    September to November 1951
  - Circulars for the Association of Western Railways, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    January to June 1952
  - Circulars for the Association of Western Railways, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    July to December 1952
  - Circulars for the Association of Western Railways, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    January to March 1953
  - Circulars for the Association of Western Railways, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    April to August 1953
  - Circulars for the Association of Western Railways, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    September to December 1953
  - Circulars for the Association of Western Railways, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    January to June 1954
  - Circulars for the Association of Western Railways, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    July to November 1954
  - Circulars for the Association of Western Railways, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    March to August 1955
  - Circulars for the Association of Western Railways, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    September to November 1955
  - Circulars for the Association of Western Railways, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    February to June 1956
  - Association of Western Railways. Circular Letters No. 248-, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Association of Western Railways. Circular Letters No. 288-, 1948 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Association of Western Railways. Circular Letters No. 390-, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Association of Western Railways. Circular Letters No. 444-, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Association of Western Railways. Circular Letters No. 494-, 1949 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Association of Western Railways. Circular Letters No. 516-, 1950 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Association of Western Railways. Circular Letters No. 548-, 1951-1956 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Association of Western Railways. Circular Letters No. 674-, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Chicago and North Western Railway System. Circulars No. S-1-, 1950-1954 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Folder 1 of 5
  - Chicago and North Western Railway System. Circulars No. S-1-, 1950-1954 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    Folder 2 of 5
  - Chicago and North Western Railway System. Circulars No. S-1-, 1950-1954 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    Folder 3 of 5
  - Chicago and North Western Railway System. Circulars No. S-1-, 1950-1954 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Folder 4 of 5
  - Chicago and North Western Railway System. Circulars No. S-1-, 1950-1954 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    Folder 5 of 5
  - Chicago and North Western Railway System. Circulars No. S-2-, 1950-1953 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Chicago and North Western Railway System. Circulars No. S-2-, 1950-1953 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Chicago and North Western Railway System. Circulars No. S-2-, 1950-1953 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Chicago and North Western Railway System. Circulars No. S-2-, 1950-1953 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Chicago and North Western Railway System. Circulars No. S-2-, 1950-1953 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Chicago and North Western Railway System. Circulars No. S-3-, 1950-1954 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    Folder 1 of 2
  - Chicago and North Western Railway System. Circulars No. S-3-, 1950-1954 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    Folder 2 of 2
  - Chicago and North Western Railway System. Circulars No. S-4-, 1951-1954 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Chicago and North Western Railway System. Circulars No. S-5-, 1952-1953 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Chicago and North Western Railway System. Circulars No. S-6-, 1950-1953 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Chicago and North Western Railway System. Circulars No. S-7-, 1951-1954 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Chicago and North Western Railway System. Circulars No. S-7-, 1951-1954 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Chicago and North Western Railway System. Circulars No. S-8-, 1951-1954 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Chicago and North Western Railway System. Circulars No. S-9-, 1950-1954 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Chicago and North Western Railway System. Circulars No. S-10-, 1949-1954 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Chicago and North Western Railway System. Circulars No. S-13-, 1950-1954 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Chicago and North Western Railway System. Circulars No. S-13-, 1950-1954 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Series III: Minneapolis and St. Louis Railway Motive Power and Operations Data, 1930-1949
  This series is comprised of information relating to Minneapolis and St. Louis Railway's [M&St.L] motive power. It includes both blank and completed forms for both the Carriers' Conference Committee and the Association of Western Railways. These spread sheets contain information on the types of motive power used by the M&St.L, the repairs made on the engines, the types of rolling stock used, and a rosters of both engines and rolling stock. These statistics are all for the month of December 1948. There are also spreadsheets documenting the number of trips made by different divisions of the M&St.L in August 1930. There are also reports on accidents.
  Of interest are the two blank questionnaires designed to test aspiring firemen and engineers on their knowledge of different types of motive power.
  - Questionnaire on the Operation of Freight Diesels 445 and 545. Blank. (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Minneapolis and St. Louis Railway Company, Mechanical Department. No date.
  - Questionnaire on the Operation of Alco Road Switches. Blank. (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Carriers' Conference Committee Forms D-49-1. Oil Burning Steam Locomotives., 1949 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    Blank.
  - Carriers' Conference Committee Forms D-49-3. Characteristics of Locomotives., 1949 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Carriers' Conference Committee Forms D-49-4. Operations of Locomotives., 1949 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    Blank
  - Carriers' Conference Committee Forms D-49-6. Rail Motor Cars., 1949 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Carriers' Conference Committee Forms D-49-7. Use of Diesel Locomotives., 1949 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Carriers' Conference Committee Forms D-49-8. Number of Diesel Locomotives., 1949 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Carriers' Conference Committee Forms D-49-9. Number of Steam Locomotives., 1949 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Carriers' Conference Committee Forms D-49-27. Number of Diesel Locomotives., 1949 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Carriers' Conference Committee Forms D-49-1. Oil-Burning Steam Locomotives. Completed., 1949 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    Minneapolis and St. Louis Railway Company. For the month ending December 31, 1948.
  - Carriers' Conference Committee Forms D-49-3. Characteristics of Locomotives. Completed., 1949 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Carriers' Conference Committee Forms D-49-4. Operation of Locomotives. Completed., 1949 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Carriers' Conference Committee Forms D-49-6. Rail Motor Cars. Completed., 1949 (Box 3, Folder 33)